<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certayne sweete prayers of the glorious name of Iesus, commonly called Iesus Mattens with the howers therto belonging / written in Latin aboue two hundred yeres agoe, by H. Susonne.</title>
            <author>Seuse, Heinrich, 1295-1366.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13150</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23443.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23170426</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23170426</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26339</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13150)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26339)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1782:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certayne sweete prayers of the glorious name of Iesus, commonly called Iesus Mattens with the howers therto belonging / written in Latin aboue two hundred yeres agoe, by H. Susonne.</title>
                  <author>Seuse, Heinrich, 1295-1366.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[55] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Carter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>between 1575 and 1578]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁸ D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Prayer-books and devotions.</term>
               <term>Books of hours --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26339:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26339:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Certayne ſweete Prayers <hi>of the glorious name of Ieſus, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called,</hi> Ieſus Mattens, <hi>with</hi>
               </hi> the howers therto belonging: written in Latin aboue two hundred yeres agoe, by <hi>H. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">A ſalutation to be ſayd in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to the euerlaſting wiſedome of God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Soule hath deſired thée in the night ſeaſon, and I haue alſo watched for thée in ſpirite and mind al the morning (O wiſedome moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent) beſéeching thée that thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
<pb facs="tcp:26339:2"/> whiche I ſo ſore haue longed for, expel from vs al ſuch thinges as are agaynſt vs, water the ſecrets of our hartes with thy manyfolde gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and mightily inflame the ſame with thy loue. And nowe my moſte ſwéete Lorde Ieſu Chriſt, I riſe and come earely to thée in the morning, and pray to thée from the botome of my hart. And a thouſande thouſande of bleſſed Saints in my name ſalute thée, and ten hundred thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande glorifie thée, who are euer in thy ſight ready at al times to doo thy will and pleaſure. I pray alſo, that the ſwéete accorde of all creatures may prayſe thée in my behalfe, and that thy triumphant name be our
<pb facs="tcp:26339:2"/> ſhielde and protection, and bleſſe vs euermore. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At euery howre this verſicle muſt be ſayde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ieſus who is the wiſedome of the Father, geue vs health both of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule.</p>
            <div type="matins">
               <head>The Mattens.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde open thou my lips. And my mouth ſhal ſhew forth thy prayſe.</p>
               <p>O God make ſpéede to ſaue me.</p>
               <p>O Lord make haſt to ſuccour me.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the father, and to the ſonne, and to the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26339:3"/>
               <p>As it was in the beginning, is nowe, and euer ſhal be world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Amen. <hi>Alleluia</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From Septuageſima til Eaſter is ſaid,</hi> Prayſe be geuen to thée O Lord, the king of eternall glory.</p>
               <div type="invitatory">
                  <head>The inuitatorie.</head>
                  <p>Pray we to the fountayne of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall wiſedome.</p>
                  <p>And let vs reioyce becauſe his name is glorious.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="Psalm">
                  <head>The Pſalme.</head>
                  <p>COme let vs reioyce vnto our Lord, let vs ſing before God our Sauiour: Let vs come before his preſence with thankes geuing, and ioyfully ſing to him in Pſalmes.</p>
                  <p>Pray we to the fountayne. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And let vs reioyce becauſe. &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:3"/>
                  <p>For our God is a great Lord, and a great king ouer all goddes, for he will not put away his people: For in his handes is al the whole earth, and he beholdeth the height of the mountaynes.</p>
                  <p>And let vs reioyce becauſe. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>For the Sea is his and he made it, and his hands haue faſhioned the dry lande: come let vs worſhip and fall downe before God, and wéepe before our Lorde that made vs, for he is our Lord God, and we are the ſhéepe of his paſture.</p>
                  <p>Prayſe we the fountayne. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And let vs reioyce becauſe. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>To day if you wil heare his voice, harden not your hart, as in the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:26339:4"/> murmuring in the day of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the wildernes, wher your fathers tempted me, proued me, and ſawe my workes.</p>
                  <p>And let vs reioyce becauſe. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Fourty yeres was I gréeued with this generation, and euer ſayd, they erre in their hartes, they haue not knowne my wayes: to whom I ſware in my anger, they ſhould not enter into my reſt.</p>
                  <p>Pray we to the fountaine of. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And let vs reioyce becauſe. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne, and to the holy ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>As it was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning, is now, and euer ſhal be world. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And let vs reioyce becauſe. &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:4"/>
                  <p>Prayſe we the fountayne of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall wiſdome.</p>
                  <p>And let vs reioyce becauſe his name is glorious.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>The Hymne.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Ieſu méeke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweteſt thought,</l>
                     <l>That yeldes eche hart true ioy:</l>
                     <l>More ſwete it is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet was ought</l>
                     <l>Thy preſence to ioioy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No ſwéeter tune or note can be</l>
                     <l>More pleaſaunt to the eare,</l>
                     <l>Nor thoght fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out ſo ſwéete as he</l>
                     <l>That is Gods ſonne and heyre.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou Ieſu hope to ſinners all,</l>
                     <l>On thée that cry with willing mind</l>
                     <l>How louing art and naturall,</l>
                     <l>To them that thée doo finde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26339:5"/>
                     <l>To Father thine al glory be,</l>
                     <l>All wiſdome eke to thée moſt pure,</l>
                     <l>The holy ghoſt in Trinitie,</l>
                     <l>Be prayſd for euer to endure. <hi>Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="Psalm">
                  <head>The Pſalme.</head>
                  <p>LEt all the earth ſing prayſe to God, let them ſay Pſalmes, and glorifie his name.</p>
                  <p>Say to God, O Lorde thy works are terrible: bicauſe of thy power which is diuers waies knowen, thy enimies will diſſemble to thée.</p>
                  <p>Let al the world honour thée, and ſing to thée, and ſay Pſalmes vnto thy name.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father, and to. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning, is nowe, and euer ſhal be. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:5"/>
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>Wiſedome hath buylded her an houſe, ſhe hath hewen out ſeuen pillers, ſhe hath brought the gentils vnder her ſubiection, &amp; by her owne might hath troden on the necke of the proude and hye minded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>I ſurely will reioyce in our Lorde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>The Reſponſe.</head>
                  <p>And will reioyce in Ieſus who is my God.</p>
                  <p>Our father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And leade vs not into temptation.</p>
                  <p>But deliuer vs from euill. Amen.</p>
                  <p>Lorde we beſéeche thée to bleſſe vs.</p>
                  <p>Ieſus who is the wiſdome of the father defende vs from all thinges that are agaynſt vs. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="lesson">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:6"/>
                  <head>The firſt Leſſon.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Wiſedome eternall, brightnes of glorie, and the very figure of the ſubſtaunce of the father, who haſte created all things of nothing, and becauſe thou wouldeſt bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine man to the pleaſure of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, thou cameſt downe into this vale of miſerie, and by thy holy con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſation thou haſt ſhewed him the path that leadeth thither, and haſt raunſomed all mankinde, as a moſt immaculate Lambe: open by thy precious death my hart, that with the eyes of a perfect beliefe I may alwayes boholde thée who art king of kinges, and lorde of Lords. Geue me wiſedome to conſider of thy
<pb facs="tcp:26339:6"/> woundes and gréeuous ſtripes, that more &amp; more I may profite in thée onely, and in thy death, who arte as a booke of charitie for me, &amp; graunt I be vtterly deſtitute of al vanities ſo that nowe I be not he whom hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto I haue bene, but that thou abide in me, &amp; I ſo linked vnto thée, that I neuer ſwarue or decline fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thée. And good Lorde I beſéeche thée haue mercy vpon vs. Thankes be to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>The Reſponſe.</head>
                  <p>Sende downe, good Lorde, thy wiſdome from the ſeate of thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that ſhe may labour and be with me, that I may know what is acceptable in thy ſight at all times.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:7"/>
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>Geue vs, O Lorde, that wiſedome that attendeth on thée, that I may knowe what is acceptable in thy ſighte at all times. Good Lorde bleſſe vs.</p>
                  <p>The euerlaſting wiſedome vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to lighten our hartes and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="lesson">
                  <head>The ſeconde Leſſon.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> My Lord Ieſu, moſt ſwéete vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, moſt bliſſeful wiſedome, the worde of the father, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ending of all kind of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: caſt thy eyes mercyfully vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me, I pray thée, for I am but fleſhe and aſhes, and I fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe that it lyeth not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:26339:7"/> muche in me, eyther to wyll any thing, or to runne, but all power commeth from thée, whoſe mercy aſſiſteth vs al. Conſider, I pray thée thy bitter paſſion which thou ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt for me a moſte wretched and vnworthy ſinner, and graciouſly continue ſuch good will as thou haſt hitherto ſhewed me. O my merciful Lorde forſake me not, O my refuge depart not from me, O my deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer make haſte to ſuccour me, and bury me in thy ſepulchre with thée, and mortifie me to the worlde, ſaue me from all deceiptes of mine eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that neither life nor death, nor no happe or chaunce ſeuer me from thée, but that our loue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue
<pb facs="tcp:26339:8"/> both now and euer, and be nothing diminiſhed by death it ſelf. And thou good Lord haue mercy vpon vs. Thankes be geuen to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>The reſponſe.</head>
                  <p>Geue me, O Lorde, that wiſedome that attendeth on thée, and put me not away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt thy children, for I am thy ſeruant, and ſonne of thy handmayde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>Sende her downe from thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſeate, that ſhe may be with me &amp; labour with me, for I am thy ſeruaunt, &amp; ſonne of thy handmaid.</p>
                  <p>Good Lorde bleſſe vs.</p>
                  <p>God the holy ghoſt repleniſhe vs with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of vnderſtanding. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="lesson">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:8"/>
                  <head>The third Leſſon.</head>
                  <p>O Lorde who art my ſuccour and helper, for that marueylous loue which cauſed thée to ſuſtaine for my ſake a moſt bitter death on the trée of the croſſe: I beſéeche thée for thy mercy ſake to pardon thoſe ſinnes which I moſt vile ſinner haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: and in the wounde of thy ſide kéepe me from accompliſhing of euyll actes, and from all dangers beſide: direct my pathes to a good ende, whyleſt I am toſſed in the waues of this life, and graunt I may come to the ſighte of eternall glory. And good Lorde haue mercy vpon me. Thankes be to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:9"/>
                  <head>The Reſponſe.</head>
                  <p>I haue loued wiſdome more then health or any beautie, and haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred her aboue the very light, and ſo all good things haue chaunced to me becauſe I enioyed her.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>I ſayd to Wiſdome, Thou art my ſiſter, and I called Prudence my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. And al good things chaunced to me when I enioyed her.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father, and to the ſonne, and to the holy ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>And all good thinges happened to me by her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This that foloweth is taken out of the ſong of S. Ambroſe, and S. Auguſtine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Thou art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of glory, O Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Thou art the euerlaſting ſonne of the father.</p>
                  <p>When thou tooke vpon thée to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer man, thou diddeſt not abhorre the virgins wombe.</p>
                  <p>When thou haddeſt ouercome the ſharpnes of death, thou opened the kingdome of heauen to al beleuers. Thou ſitteſt on the right hande of God, in the glory of thy father.</p>
                  <p>We beléeue that thou wilt come to be our Iudge.</p>
                  <p>Therfore we beſéech thée to helpe thy ſeruauntes, whom thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demed with thy moſt precious blood.</p>
                  <p>Cauſe them to be numbred with thy Saints in glory euerlaſting.
<pb facs="tcp:26339:10"/> Saue thy people, O Lord, and bleſſe thine heritage.</p>
                  <p>Gouerne them, and lift them vp for euer.</p>
                  <p>And we prayſe thy name euer world without ende.</p>
                  <p>Vouchſafe, O Lorde, to kéepe vs this day without ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Haue mercy vpon vs, O Lorde, haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
                  <p>Let thy mercy light vpon vs, as our truſt is in thée.</p>
                  <p>In thée, O Lorde, haue I truſted, let me neuer be confounded. Amen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thoſe that wil, may ſay in place of this, that which foloweth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WE prayſe thée, O Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>We bleſſe thée, O Ieſu.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:10"/>
                  <p>We confeſſe thée to be the king of kings, and lorde of al lordes.</p>
                  <p>We worſhip thee who was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, our ſweete &amp; louing Redemer.</p>
                  <p>Who ſaued vs by the ſhedding of thy blood.</p>
                  <p>Thou art worthy, Lord Ieſu our God, to haue prayſe, bleſſing, glory, and honour.</p>
                  <p>All fleſhe reioyſeth to thee, and all liuing creatures glorifie thy name.</p>
                  <p>Let al things bow vnder thy fete, and al creatures ſerue thee.</p>
                  <p>Let them prayſe &amp; magnifie thee, bleſſe and glorifie thee for euer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="lauds">
               <head>The Laudes.</head>
               <p>Ieſus who is the wiſedome of the father, giue vs health both of body
<pb facs="tcp:26339:11"/> and ſoule.</p>
               <p>O God make ſpeede to helpe vs.</p>
               <p>O Lord make haſt to ſuccour vs.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the father, to the. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As it was in the beginning, is. &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="Psalm">
                  <head>The Pſalme.</head>
                  <p>PRayſe our Lorde al ye Gentiles, prayſe him all ye Nations.</p>
                  <p>For his mercy hath bene ſhewed in vs, and the truth of our Lorde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydeth for euer.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father, to the. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>Wiſdome cryeth out in the ſtree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: If any man loueth wiſdome, let him bowe to me and he ſhal find her out: and he that hath found her,
<pb facs="tcp:26339:11"/> happie is he if he can keepe her.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>The Chapiter.</head>
                  <p>This wiſdome I haue loued, and haue ſought for her from my youth hitherto, and haue made meanes ſhe might be my wife, and I was taken with her beautie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere,</hi> Thankes be to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>The Hymne.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Ieſu wondrous king,</l>
                     <l>That doſt triumph in bliſſe:</l>
                     <l>To all men thee deſiring,</l>
                     <l>Thy ioy exceeding is.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No tong hath ſhewde by ſpeache,</l>
                     <l>Ne letters euer tolde,</l>
                     <l>Nor Ieſus loue may teache,</l>
                     <l>But triall can vnfolde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26339:12"/>
                     <l>O pearles Ieſus loue,</l>
                     <l>For which I languiſhe ſore,</l>
                     <l>My hart with pleaſure moue</l>
                     <l>Of thée my hart and ſtore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All wiſedome be to thée,</l>
                     <l>And to thy father glory,</l>
                     <l>The holy ghoſt prayſe wée,</l>
                     <l>One God in perſons thrée. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>Wiſedome reſteth in his harte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>The Reſponſe.</head>
                  <p>And prudence abideth in the words of his mouth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>O thou wiſedome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>The ſong of Zacharias.</head>
                  <p>BLeſſed be the Lord god of Iſrael, for he hath viſited and redéemed
<pb facs="tcp:26339:12"/> his people.</p>
                  <p>And hath lifted vp an horne of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatien, in the houſe of his ſeruaunt Dauid.</p>
                  <p>As he ſpake by the mouth of his holy Prophetes, whiche haue béene ſince the world began.</p>
                  <p>That we ſhould be ſaued from our enimies, and from the hands of all that hate vs.</p>
                  <p>To ſhewe mercy to our fathers, and to remember his holy couenant</p>
                  <p>To performe the othe whiche he ſware to our father Abraham, of ſuche things as he would geue vs.</p>
                  <p>That beeing deliuered from the hands of our enimies, we woulde ſerue him without feare.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:13"/>
                  <p>In holines &amp; righteouſnes before him al the dayes of our life.</p>
                  <p>And thou childe ſhalt be called the prophet of the higheſt, for thou ſhalt go before his face to prepare his wayes.</p>
                  <p>To geue knowledge of ſaluation to his people, for the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>Through the tender mercy of God, by whiche he hath viſited vs ſpringing from an high.</p>
                  <p>To geue light to them that ſit in darknes, &amp; in the ſhadowe of death, to guide our féete in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of peace.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father, to the ſon, and to the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:13"/>
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Thou wiſedome which procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of the mouth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyeſt, that reacheth from one ende of the world to an other, who doth ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place all thinges in a comely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: come and teache vs the way howe to attayne thy wiſdome.</p>
                  <p>Lorde heare my prayer.</p>
                  <p>And let my crye come to thée.</p>
                  <p>Let vs pray.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Lord who by thy wiſdome whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is eternal, as thou thy ſelfe art, created man who before was not, and when he was vtterly loſte, did moſt mercyfully redéeme him: graunt we beſéeche thée, that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the inſpiration of the ſaid wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:26339:14"/> into our hartes, we may loue thée with all our minds, and runne to thée with all our harte: through our ſayde Lorde Ieſus Chriſte thy ſonne, who liueth &amp; raigneth with thée in the vnitie of the holy Ghoſt, God world without ende. Amen.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe we the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>Thankes be to God.</p>
                  <p>The euerlaſting wiſdome bleſſe &amp; kéepe our minds &amp; bodies. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prime">
               <head>The Pryme.</head>
               <p>Ieſus who is the wiſdome of the father, geue vs health both of body and ſoule.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26339:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> God make ſpéede to helpe me.</p>
               <p>O Lord make haſt to ſuccor me.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the father, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne, and to the holy ghoſt.</p>
               <p>As it was in the beginning, is nowe, and euer ſhal be world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Amen.</p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>The Hymne.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O loue of Ieſu ſwéete,</l>
                     <l>A hundred folde I ſay,</l>
                     <l>More gentle to intreate,</l>
                     <l>Then ſhewe with words I may.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Angelical comfort ſure,</l>
                     <l>To taſte as honey ſwéete.</l>
                     <l>To heare no better pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>And to our hart fine meate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou bleſſed Ieſu daunt</l>
                     <l>My hart with loue of thée,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26339:15"/>
                     <l>Thy preſence doo me graunt,</l>
                     <l>In glory for to ſée.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To father thine all glory be,</l>
                     <l>Al wiſedome eke to thée moſt pure,</l>
                     <l>The holy ghoſt in Trinitie,</l>
                     <l>Be prayſd for euer to endure. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="Psalm">
                  <head>The Pſalme</head>
                  <p>CAuſe me to heare of thy mercy in the morning, for I haue put my truſt in thée.</p>
                  <p>Let me knowe the way wherein I may walke, for I haue lift vp my hart to thée.</p>
                  <p>Deliuer me from my enimies, O Lord I fled to thée for ſuccour: teach me to do thy wil, for thou art my god</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:15"/>
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>I loue ſuche as loue me, and thoſe that earely watche for me, ſhall finde me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>The Chapiter.</head>
                  <p>WIſdome ſurpaſſeth wickednes, and ſpreadeth from coaſte to coaſte, who doth ſtrongly place all things in a ſéemely order.</p>
                  <p>Thankes be to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The Anſwere.</head>
                  <p>Ieſu Chriſte ſonne of the liuing God, haue mercy vpon me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>Thou that ſitteſt on the righte hande of God, haue mercy vpon vs,</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Ieſu Chriſte ſonne of the liuing
<pb facs="tcp:26339:16"/> God, haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>Ariſe, O Lorde, and helpe vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Aunſwere.</head>
                  <p>And deliuer vs for thy holy name ſake.</p>
                  <p>O Lorde heare my prayer.</p>
                  <p>And let my cry come vnto thée.</p>
                  <p>Let vs pray.</p>
                  <p>Let the brightnes (O Lorde) of thy eternall wiſedome illuminate our harts, that they be not dimmed with the darknes of this world, but that we may come to that countrey where is perpetual light: through our ſayde Lorde Ieſus Chriſte thy ſonne. And ſo foorth, as before.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="terce">
               <pb facs="tcp:26339:16"/>
               <head>The third howre.</head>
               <p>Ieſus who is the wiſedome of the father, geue vs health both of body and ſoule.</p>
               <p>O God make ſpéede to helpe me.</p>
               <p>O Lord make haſt to ſuccour me.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As it was in the. &amp;c. <hi>Alleluia.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>The Hymne.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thy loue, O Ieſu, is</l>
                     <l>A paſſing ſwéete repaſte,</l>
                     <l>Not lothſome ought iwis,</l>
                     <l>But ſuger all in taſte.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That thée do taſt, they hunger ſtil,</l>
                     <l>They drinke and yet are dry,</l>
                     <l>They wold none haue by their good will,</l>
                     <l>Saue Ieſus him on hye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26339:17"/>
                     <l>A thouſande times I thée deſire,</l>
                     <l>How glad thou wouldſt me make,</l>
                     <l>If thou wilt come as I require,</l>
                     <l>And cauſe my hunger ſlake.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All wiſedome be to thée,</l>
                     <l>And to thy father glory,</l>
                     <l>The holy ghoſt prayſe wée,</l>
                     <l>One God in perſons thrée. Amen.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="Psalm">
                  <head>The Pſalme.</head>
                  <p>THy holy ſpirite will bring me to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right path, for thy name ſake.</p>
                  <p>O Lorde quicken me in thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Thou wilt bring my ſoule out of all miſerie: and in thy mercy thou wilt deſtroy all my enimies.</p>
                  <p>And wilt deſtroy al thoſe that trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble my ſoule, for I am thy ſeruant.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:17"/>
                  <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>My ſonne if thou couet wiſdome, kéepe Iuſtice, and our Lorde wyll geue her thée.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>The Chapiter.</head>
                  <p>This wiſdome I haue loued and ſought for fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my youth, and ſought howe I mighte haue her for my ſpouſe, and was rauiſhed with her beautie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Thanks be to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Reſponſe.</head>
                  <p>I wil ſurely reioyce in our Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>And ſolace my ſelf in Ieſus my god.</p>
                  <p>I will reioyce in our Lorde.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:18"/>
                  <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I wil ſurely reioyce in our Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>Verſicle.</head>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the name of our Lorde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>The Reſponſe.</head>
                  <p>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth world without ende.</p>
                  <p>Let vs pray.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> God, who by thy eternal wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome madeſt man, who before that was not at all, &amp; after he was loſt diddeſt mercifully redéeme him: graunt we beſéeche thée, that by the ſame mercy inſpiring our harts, we may loue thée with al our harts, and with all our ſtrength runne vnto thée: through our ſayd Lord Ieſus Chriſte thy ſonne. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="sext">
               <pb facs="tcp:26339:18"/>
               <head>The ſight howre.</head>
               <p>Ieſus the wiſdome of the Father, geue vs health both of body &amp; ſoule.</p>
               <p>O God make ſpéede to helpe me.</p>
               <p>O Lord make haſt to ſuccour me.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the father.</p>
               <p>As it was in the. &amp;c. <hi>Alleluia.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>The Hymne.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ieſu from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al bounty ſprings,</l>
                     <l>A ioy of minde for aye,</l>
                     <l>An vnſpeakable wondrous thing,</l>
                     <l>That ſteales my hart away.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Beſt is for me to leaue this pelfe,</l>
                     <l>And Ieſu to ſéeke out:</l>
                     <l>I will rather forſake my ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſu leaue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath me bought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26339:19"/>
                     <l>O louely Ieſu méeke,</l>
                     <l>A hope to them that for thée longs:</l>
                     <l>Thée gracious teares doo ſéeke,</l>
                     <l>With drierie mournful ſongs.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To father thine al glory be,</l>
                     <l>Al wiſedome eke to thée moſt pure,</l>
                     <l>The holy ghoſt in Trinitie,</l>
                     <l>Be prayſd for euer to endure. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="Psalm">
                  <head>The Pſalme.</head>
                  <p>OVr ſoule paciently loketh for our Lorde, for he is our helper and our refuge.</p>
                  <p>For our hart ſhal reioice in him, &amp; we haue truſt in his holy name.</p>
                  <p>Lord let thy mercy be ſhewed vnto vs: as we haue put our truſt in thee</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:19"/>
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>Our Lord had poſſeſſion of me in the beginning of his wayes: he had me before he begonne any of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, in the beginning ſayth our Lorde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>The Chapiter.</head>
                  <p>The brightnes of euerlaſting light, the glaſſe of eternal maieſtie, which is cleare without any ſpot, &amp; the very paterne of his goodnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Thankes be to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>The Reſponſe.</head>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the name of our Lorde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth world without end.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the Father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the name of our Lorde.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:20"/>
                  <p>From henceforth world without ende.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>Verſicle.</head>
                  <p>From the riſing of the Sunne, to the going downe thereof.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the name of our Lorde.</p>
                  <p>Let vs pray.</p>
                  <p>GEue eare to vs O merciful god, and ſhewe the brightnes of thy wiſdome vnto our mindes, graunt we may loue thée aboue al thinges, through our ſaid Lorde Ieſus. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="nones">
               <head>The ninth howre.</head>
               <p>Ieſus the wiſdome of the father, geue vs health both of body &amp; ſoule.</p>
               <p>O God make ſpéede to helpe me.</p>
               <p>O Lord make haſt to ſuccour me.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the. &amp;c. As it was. &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:20"/>
                  <head>The Hymne.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What coaſtes to trace I minde,</l>
                     <l>I Ieſu alwayes would:</l>
                     <l>Howe glad if I him finde,</l>
                     <l>But bliſſe if I him holde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then clipping and kiſſing,</l>
                     <l>That paſſeth pleaſure all:</l>
                     <l>In theſe without ſtaying,</l>
                     <l>I will to Ieſus call.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nowe what I ſought I finde,</l>
                     <l>And founde I holde at laſte:</l>
                     <l>For Ieſus loue I pinde,</l>
                     <l>And burnt within full faſte.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All wiſedome be to thée.</l>
                     <l>And to thy father glory,</l>
                     <l>The holy ghoſt prayſe we,</l>
                     <l>One God in perſons thrée.</l>
                     <l>Amen.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="Psalm">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:21"/>
                  <head>The Pſalme.</head>
                  <p>CReate in me (O Lorde) a pure harte, and renue in me a perfect ſpirite.</p>
                  <p>Caſt me not away from thy face, and take not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me thy holy ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Reſtore to me the gladnes of thy ſaluation, and ſtrengthen me with a principal ſpirite.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father, to the. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning, is. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>Before the déepes and ſeas were, I was borne: when he went about to create the heauens I was with him, and ſet al things in order.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>The Chapiter.</head>
                  <p>WIſdome is more goodly than the ſunne and all other ſtarres that
<pb facs="tcp:26339:21"/> are placed in ſo goodly an order, and if it be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with the very light, it is certayne it was before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Thankes be to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Reſponſe.</head>
                  <p>From the riſing of the Sunne to the going downe thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>The name of our Lorde is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be prayſed.</p>
                  <p>Vntill the going downe therof.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>From the riſing of the ſunne, tyll the going downe thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> Wiſedome reſteth in his hart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> And prudence in the words of his mouth.</p>
                  <p>Let vs pray.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:22"/>
                  <p>POwer into our harts (O Lorde) the light of thy wiſdome, that we may knowe thée truely, &amp; faythfully loue thée: through our ſayde Lorde Ieſus Chriſt thy ſonne, who liueth and reigneth with thée in the vnity of the holy Ghoſt, God world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Amen.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe we the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>Thankes be to God.</p>
                  <p>The euerlaſting wiſedome bleſſe &amp; kéepe our hartes &amp; bodies. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Vespers">
               <head>Euenſong.</head>
               <p>Ieſus the wiſdome of the Father, geue vs health both of body and ſoule.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26339:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> God make ſpéede to ſuccour me.</p>
               <p>O Lorde make haſt to helpe me.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As it was in the. &amp;c. <hi>Alleluia.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="Psalm">
                  <head>The Pſalme.</head>
                  <p>OVr lord hath ſent redemption to his people, he hath commaunded his teſtament to be inuiolatly kept for euer.</p>
                  <p>His name is holy and terrible, the feare of our Lorde is the beginning of wiſedome.</p>
                  <p>Vnderſtanding is good to all ſuche as doo exerciſe it, his prayſe endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for euermore.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the Father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:23"/>
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>All wiſedome commeth from our Lorde God, and was with him at al times, and is ſtill for euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>The Chapiter.</head>
                  <p>This wiſedome I haue loued, and ſought for her, ſince my youth I haue ſought how I might enioy her as my ſpouſe, and I was inflamed with her beautie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Thanks be to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>The Hymne.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Ieſu clearer then the ſunne,</l>
                     <l>No ſwéeter balme than thée:</l>
                     <l>No ſwéete like thée, not one,</l>
                     <l>Aboue al things moſt frée.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou art the ende of loue,</l>
                     <l>That giueth delight of minde:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26339:23"/>
                     <l>My glory eke art thou,</l>
                     <l>That ſauedſt all mankinde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Encreace of mercy euermore</l>
                     <l>Thou art, and hope of ioy:</l>
                     <l>Of grace the well and ſtore,</l>
                     <l>That ſheldeſt from anoy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To father thine all glory be,</l>
                     <l>Al wiſedome eke to thée moſt pure,</l>
                     <l>The holy ghoſt in Trinitie,</l>
                     <l>Be prayſd for euer to endure.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="versicle">
                  <head>The verſicle.</head>
                  <p>I will ſurely reioyce in our Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p>And ſolace my ſelf in my god Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antheme.</hi> O orient brightnes. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſong of the virgin Mary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My ſoule doth magnifie our Lord. And my ſpirite hath reioyced in
<pb facs="tcp:26339:24"/> God my ſauiour.</p>
                  <p>For he hath behelde the humilitie of his handmayde: beholde from henceforth all generations ſhal cal me bleſſed.</p>
                  <p>For he that is mightie hath mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified me, and holy is his name.</p>
                  <p>And his mercy is alwaies ſhewed to them that feare him, throughout all generations.</p>
                  <p>He hath ſhewed ſtrength with his arme, he hath ſcattered the proude in the imagination of their harts.</p>
                  <p>He hath put downe the mightie from their ſeate, and hath exalted the humble and méeke.</p>
                  <p>He hath filled the hungry with good thinges, and the riche he hath
<pb facs="tcp:26339:24"/> ſent emptie away.</p>
                  <p>He hath remembred his mercy, &amp; deliuered his ſeruaunt Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>As he promiſed our fathers, and Abraham and his ſéede for euer.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <head>Antheme.</head>
                  <p>O orient brightnes of eternall lighte, and ſonne of Iuſtice, come and lighten vs that ſit in darknes, and in the ſhadowe of death.</p>
                  <p>Lorde heare my prayer.</p>
                  <p>And let my crye come to thée.</p>
                  <p>Let vs pray.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> God who by thy eternall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome made man, who before
<pb facs="tcp:26339:25"/> that time was not at all, and after he fell, diddeſt mercifully redéeme him: graunt we beſéeche thée, that by the ſame wiſdome inſpiring our hartes, we may loue thée with all our hartes, and runne vnto thée with all our mighte: through our ſayde Lord Ieſus Chriſt thy ſonne, who liueth and reigneth with thée in the vnitie of the holy ghoſt, God worlde without ende. Amen.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe we our Lorde.</p>
                  <p>Thankes be to God.</p>
                  <p>The eurlaſting wiſedome bleſſe and kéepe our hartes and bodyes.</p>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="compline">
               <pb facs="tcp:26339:25"/>
               <head>Compline.</head>
               <p>Ieſus the wiſedome of the father, geue vs health both of body &amp; ſoule.</p>
               <p>Conuert vs God our Sauiour.</p>
               <p>And turne thy wrath away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.</p>
               <p>O God make ſpéede to ſaue me.</p>
               <p>O Lord make haſt to ſuccour me.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the father, to the ſon, and to the holy ghoſt.</p>
               <p>As it was in the beginning, is nowe, and euer ſhal be world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Amen. <hi>Alleluia.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="Psalm">
                  <head>The Pſalme.</head>
                  <p>LIghten mine eyes that I neuer ſléepe in death, leſt mine enimie at any time ſay, I haue preuayled ouer him.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe that perſecute me will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce
<pb facs="tcp:26339:26"/> if I be moued, but I truſt in thy mercy.</p>
                  <p>My harte ſhall reioyce in thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
                  <p>I will ſing vnto our Lorde, who hath geuen me good things: and ſing to the name of the hyeſt.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>I dwell in the hyeſt places, and my throne is in the pillers of the cloudes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>The Chapiter.</head>
                  <p>WIſedome teacheth ſobrietie, righteouſnes and vertue, which thinges be moſt commodious for vs in this life.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Thanks be to God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſponſe.</hi> In good quietnes, I will ſléepe and take my reſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſicle.</hi> If I ſléepe and take a nappe with mine eyes.</p>
                  <p>I will ſléepe and take my reſt.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>In good quietnes I wil ſléepe, and take my reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hymn">
                  <head>The Hymne.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nowe Ieſus rules in peace,</l>
                     <l>Which tongue can not expreſſe:</l>
                     <l>My minde deſires &amp; will not ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>But néedes wil haue to him acceſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Saintes in heauen glad,</l>
                     <l>To prayſe thée be not ſlacke:</l>
                     <l>Ieſus gladdes the world bad,</l>
                     <l>And for vs peace w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god doth make.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26339:27"/>
                     <l>Ieſu to heauen did aſcende,</l>
                     <l>Vnto his Princely throne:</l>
                     <l>My harte is after Ieſus wende,</l>
                     <l>And lefte me all alone.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All wiſedome be to thée,</l>
                     <l>And to thy father glory,</l>
                     <l>The holy ghoſt prayſe we,</l>
                     <l>One God in perſons thrée. Amen.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſicle.</hi> His place is made ready in peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> And his habitation in Sion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>O glorious king.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head>The ſong of Simeon.</head>
                  <p>LOrde nowe letteſt thou thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant depart in peace, according to thy worde.</p>
                  <p>For mine eyes haue ſéene thy
<pb facs="tcp:26339:27"/> ſaluation, which thou haſt prepared before the face of all people.</p>
                  <p>A light to lighten the Gentiles, and to be the glory of the people Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father, to the ſon, and to the holy ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the beginning, is nowe, and euer ſhal be world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="anthem">
                  <head>The Antheme.</head>
                  <p>O glorious King, who art alwayes prayſed among thy Saintes, and yet no man can ſpeake ſo worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of thée as thy Maieſtie requireth, thou Lorde art among vs, and thy holy name is called vpon by vs, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake vs not our God, but at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme
<pb facs="tcp:26339:28"/> day of Iudgement, vouchſafe to place vs among thy choſen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts and Saintes, moſte bleſſed king.</p>
                  <p>Lorde heare my prayer.</p>
                  <p>And let my cry come vnto thée.</p>
                  <p>Let vs pray.</p>
                  <p>Mercyfully (O Lorde) looke vpon our frayltie, and fauourably geue vs a taſte of thy celeſtiall wiſdome, that when we haue taſted of the merueylous ſwéetenes thereof, we may deſpiſe all worldly vanitie, and continually with burning de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire cleaue vnto thée, who arte the chéefeſt goodnes that may be: tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough our ſayd Lorde Ieſus Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:26339:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> thy ſonne, who liueth and reigneth with thée in the vnitie of the holy ghoſt, God worlde without ende. Amen.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe we our Lorde.</p>
                  <p>Thankes be to God.</p>
                  <p>The euerlaſting wiſedome bleſſe and kéepe our mindes and bodyes.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26339:29"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
